So I think data can actually make us more human.
اعتقد ان البيانات يمكنها حقا ان تجعلنا اكثر انسانية
We're collecting and creating all kinds of data about how we're living our lives,
اننا نجمع و نخلق كل انواع البيانات عن كيف نعيش حياتنا
and it's enabling us to tell some amazing stories.
وهي تمكننا من سرد بعض القصص الرائعة
Recently, a wise media theorist Tweeted,
مؤخرا، باحث اعلامي حكيم اعلن على تويتر
"The 19th century culture was defined by the novel,
"حضارة القرن 19 حددت بالقصة،
the 20th century culture was defined by the cinema,
و حضارة القرن 20 حددت بالسينما،
and the culture of the 21st century
و حضارة القرن 21
will be defined by the interface."
سوف تحدد بالوسائط."
And I believe this is going to prove true.
وإنني أؤمن أنه سوف يثبت صحته
Our lives are being driven by data,
فحياتنا تقودها البيانات،
and the presentation of that data is an opportunity
وعرض هذه البيانات هي فرصة
for us to make some amazing interfaces that tell great stories.
لنا لصنع بعض الوسائط الرائعة والتي تحكي قصص عظيمة.
So I'm going to show you a few of the projects
لذا سوف أريكم بعض المشاريع
that I've been working on over the last couple years
التي كنت أعمل عليها على مدار الأعوام الماضية
that reflect on our lives and our systems.
والتي تؤثر على حياتنا وأنظمتنا.
This is a project called Flight Patterns.
هذا المشروع يسمى نمط رحلات الطيران.
What you're looking at is airplane traffic
ما ترونه هو حركة مرور الطائرات
over North America for a 24-hour period.
فوق أمريكا الشمالية خلال مدة 24 ساعة.
As you see, everything starts to fade to black,
كما ترون ، كل شيء بدأ بالاختفاء في العدم،
and you see people going to sleep.
وترون الناس تذهب الى النوم.
Followed by that, you see on the West coast
بعد هذا، تشاهدون على الشاطىء الغربي
planes moving across, the red-eye flights to the East coast.
طائرات تتحرك تعبر، الرحلات الحمراء وصولا للبر الشرقي.
And you'll see everybody waking up on the East coast,
ثم ستشاهدون الناس جميعا تستيقظ في الشاطىء الشرقي،
followed by European flights coming in the upper right-hand corner.
تليها الرحلات الأوروبية قادمة من الجانب العلوي الأيمن.
Everybody's moving from the East coast to the West coast.
جميع الناس تسافر من الشاطىء الشرقي الى الشاطىء الغربي.
You see San Francisco and Los Angeles
تشاهد سان فرانسيسكو ولوس انجلوس
start to make their journeys down to Hawaii in the lower left-hand corner.
حيث تبدا رحلاتهم المتجهة الى الأسفل حيث هاواي في الجانب السفلي الأيسر.
I think it's one thing to say there's 140,000 planes
أعتقد أنه القول بأن هناك 140,000 طائرة
being monitored by the federal government at any one time,
تراقب من طرف الحكومة الفدرالية في نفس الوقت، أمر
and it's another thing to see that system as it ebbs and flows.
ورؤية هذا النظام يتدفق وينحسر هو أمر آخر.
This is a time-lapse image of that exact same data,
وهذه صورة زمنية لنفس البيانات،
but I've color-coded it by type,
ولكني أعطيتها ألوانا بحسب نوعها،
so you can see the diversity of aircraft that are in the skies above us.
حيث بامكانكم ان تروا اختلاف الطائرات في السماء من فوقنا.
And I started making these, and I put them into Google Maps
وبدأت في صنع هذه ، ثم وضعتها على خرائط جوجل
and allow you to zoom in and see individual airports
وسمحت ان تقرب الصورة لترى المطارات كل على حدى
and the patterns that are occurring there.
والأنماط التي تحدث هناك.
So here we can see the white represents low altitudes,
فهنا نرى الأبيض يمثل الارتفاعات المنخفضة،
and the blue are higher altitudes.
والأزرق يمثل الأرتفاعات الأكثر علوا.
And you can zoom in. This is taking a look at Atlanta.
ويمكنك ان تقوم بالتكبير. و هنا نلقى نظرة على اطلنطا
You can see this is a major shipping airport,
بإمكانك أن ترى أنه مطار شحن رئيسي،
and there's all kinds of activity there.
وفيه كل أنواع الأنشطة.
You can also toggle between altitude
بمكانك ايضا ان تبدل بين الارتفاعات
for model and manufacturer.
للنوع والمصنع.
See again, the diversity.
شاهد مرة أخرى، الاختلاف.
And you can scroll around and see
ويمكنك ان تتنقل لترى
some of the different airports and the different patterns that they have.
بعض المطارات المختلفة و أنماطها المختلفة.
This is scrolling up the East coast.
هنا ننتقل للأعلى حيث الساحل الشرقي.
You can see some of the chaos that's happening in New York
يمكنك ان ترى القليل من الفوضى التي تحدث في نيويورك
with the air traffic controllers
مع وحدات التحكم في المرور الجوي
having to deal with all those major airports next to each other.
التي يجب عليها ان تتعامل مع كل تلك المطارات الرئيسية بجانب بعضها البعض.
So zooming back out real quick,
ونعود ونبتعد بسرعة،
we see, again, the U.S. -- you get Florida down in the right-hand corner.
نرى، مرة أخرى ، الولايات المتحدة -- و أسفل في الجانب الأيمن تجد فلوريدا.
Moving across to the West coast,
وننتقل الى الساحل الغربي،
you see San Francisco and Los Angeles --
يمكنكم رؤية سان فرانسيسكو و لوس انجلوس--
big low-traffic zones
مناطق ذات نسبة مرور منخفضة
across Nevada and Arizona.
مرورا بنيفادا واريزونا.
And that's us down there in L.A. and Long Beach on the bottom.
وها نحن في الأسفل في لوس انجلوس و لونج بيتش.
I started taking a look as well at different perimeters,
وبدأت القي نظرة أيضا على مختلف المناطق المحيطة،
because you can choose what you want to pull out from the data.
لأن بامكانك اختيار ما تريد إظهاره من البيانات.
This is looking at ascending versus descending flights.
وهنا نشاهد الرحلات الصاعدة في مقابل الرحلات الهابطة.
And you can see, over time, the ways the airports change.
وبامكانك ان ترى كيف تتغير المطارات مع مرور الوقت.
You see the holding patterns that start to develop
يمكنك أن ترى الأنماط المستقرة والتي تبدأ في النمو
in the bottom of the screen.
في أسفل الشاشة.
And you can see, eventually the airport actually flips directions.
وبامكانك ان ترى أخيرا المطار وهو يعكس اتجاهه.
So this is another project that I worked on with the Sensible Cities Lab at MIT.
والآن هذا مشروع آخر عملت عليه مع مختبر المدن الحساسة في MIT.
This is visualizing international communications.
انه يصور الاتصالات العالمية.
So it's how New York communicates
وبالتالي هو حول كيف تتواصل نيويورك
with other international cities.
مع باقي المدن العالمية.
And we set this up as a live globe in the Museum of Modern Art in New York
وقد أقمنا هذا المشورع ككرة أرضية حية في متحف الفن الحديث في نيويورك
for the Design the Elastic Mind exhibition.
كتصميم في معرض مرونة العقل.
And it had a live feed with a 24-hour offset,
وقد توفر على تغذية حية على مدار 24 ساعة،
so you could see the changing relationship
فبامكانك ان ترى العلاقة المتغيرة
and some demographic info
وبعض البيانات الديموغرافية
coming through AT&amp;T's data and revealing itself.
آتية من خلال بيانات AT&amp;T و مظهرة نفسها.
This is another project I worked on with Sensible Cities Lab
وهذا مشورع آخر عملنا عليه بالاشتراك مع مختبر المدن الحساسة
and CurrentCity.org.
و CurrentCity.org
And it's visualizing SMS messages being sent in the city of Amsterdam.
وهو يصور الرسائل النصية المرسلة في مدينة امستردام.
So you're seeing the daily ebb and flow
لذا فانت تشاهد الانحسار والتدفق اليومي
of people sending SMS messages from different parts of the city,
للناس وهم يرسلون الرسائل من مختلف مناطق المدينة،
until we approach New Year's Eve, where everybody says, "Happy New Year!"
حتى نقترب من ليلة رأس السنة. عندما يقول الجميع "سنة سعيدة!"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So this is an interactive tool
لذا فهذه أداة تفاعلية.
that you can move around and see different parts of the city.
بامكانك ان تتحرك وتشاهد مختلف المناطق من المدينة.
This is looking at another event. This is called Queen's Day.
وهنا نرى مناسبة أخرى. تسمى "يوم الملكة".
So again, you get this daily ebb and flow
ومرة أخرى، نرى التدفق والانسحاب اليومي
of people sending SMS messages from different parts of the city.
والناس ترسل الرسائل النصية من مختلف مناطق المدينة.
And then you're going to see people start to gather in the center of the city
ثم نشاهد ان الناس تبدأ في التجمع في وسط المدينة
to celebrate the night before,
لتحتفل بالليلة السابقة،
which happens right here.
وهو ما يحدث هنا.
And then you can see people celebrating the next day.
ثم ترى الناس يحتفلون في اليوم التالي.
And you can pause it and step back and forth and see different phases.
ويمكنك ان توقفها وتنتقل الى السابق والتالي لترى الفترات المختلفة.
So now on to something completely different.
والآن ننتقل الى شيء مختلف تماما.
Some of you may recognize this.
بامكان بعضكم تمييز هذا.
This is Baron Wolfgang von Kempelen's mechanical chess playing machine.
هذه هي لعبة الشطرنج الميكانيكية للبارون وولف فون كيمبلين.
And it's this amazing robot that plays chess extremely well,
وهي عبارة عن انسان آلي يلعب الشطرنج بمهارة،
except for one thing: it's not a robot at all.
ما عدا شيء واحد: انه ليس انسان آلي بأي شكل.
There's actually a legless man that sits in that box
في الحقيقة ، هناك رجل بدون أرجل يجلس في ذاك الصندوق
and controls this chess player.
ويتحكم بلاعب الشطرنج هذا.
This was the inspiration for a web service by Amazon
وهذا كان الالهام في خدمة أنترنيت من "أمازون"
called the Mechanical Turk -- named after this guy.
سميت "ترك الآلي" - سميت على اسم ذلك الرجل.
And it's based on the premise that there are certain things
وهي قائمة على افتراض أساسي بأن هناك أشياء معينة
that are easy for people, but really difficult for computers.
سهلة على الأشخاص، وصعبة حقا على الحواسيب.
So they made this web service and said,
ولذلك انشأوا هذه الخدمة وقالوا،
"Any programmer can write a piece of software
" أي مبرمج بامكانه أن يكتب جزء من البرنامج
and tap into the minds of thousands of people."
وأن يستغل عقول آلاف الناس."
The nerdy side of me thought, "Wow, this is amazing.
الجانب المهووس مني فكر، "واو، هذا رائع.
I can tap into thousands of people's minds."
بامكاني استغلال عقول آلاف الناس."
And the other nerdy side of me thought,
والجانب المهووس الآخر مني فكر،
"This is horrible. This is completely bizarre.
" هذا رهيب. هذا غريب تماما.
What does this mean for the future of mankind,
ماذا يعني هذا لمستقبل الانسانية
where we're all plugged into this borg?"
حيث كلنا متصلين بهذا البرج؟"
I was probably being a little extreme.
ربما كنت مبالغا بعض الشيء.
But what does this mean when we have no context for what it is that we're working on,
ولكن ماذا يعني هذا ونحن لا نملك سياقا لما نعمل عليه،
and we're just doing these little labors?
نبذل فقط تلك الجهود؟
So I created this drawing tool.
ولذلك صنعت أداة الرسم هاته.
I asked people to draw a sheep facing to the left.
طلبت من الناس ان ترسم خروف متجه للشمال.
And I said, "I'll pay you two cents for your contribution."
وقلت ، " سأدفع قرشين لمساهمتك."
And I started collecting sheep.
وبدأت في جمع الخرفان.
And I collected a lot, a lot of different sheep.
وجمعت الكثير والكثير من الخرفان المختلفة.
Lots of sheep.
الكثير من الخرفان.
I took the first 10,000 sheep that I collected,
أخذت 10000 خرفان الأولى التي جمعتها،
and I put them on a website called TheSheepMarket.com
ووضعتها على موقع انترنت يسمى TheSheepMarket.com
where you can actually buy collections of 20 sheep.
حيث يمكنك ان تشتري مجموعة من 20 خروفا.
You can't pick individual sheep,
لا يمكنك اختيار خروف معين،
but you can buy a single plate block of stamps as a commodity.
ولكن يمكنك أن تشتري مجموعة من العينات بالجملة.
And juxtaposed against this grid,
ووضعا جنبا الى جنب مقابل هذه الشبكة،
you see actually, by rolling over each individual one,
بإمكانك ان ترى حقا، لدى مرورك على كل منها،
the humanity behind this hugely mechanical process.
الانسانية خلف كل هذه العملية الميكانيكية الضخمة.
I think there's something really interesting
أعتقد انه أمر مثيرا حقا
to watching people as they go through this creative toil --
وأنت تشاهد الناس وهم يمرون بهذه الأداة المبدعة --
something we can all relate to,
أمر بامكاننا جميعا التواصل معه،
this creative process of trying to come up with something from nothing.
هذه العملية الابداعية وأنت تحاول خلق شيء من لاشيء.
I think it was really interesting to juxtapose this humanity
اعتقد انه كان شيقا ان نضع هذه الانسانيات بجلنب بعضها البعض
versus this massive distributed grid.
في مقابل الشبكة الضخمة من التوزيع.
Kind of amazing what some people did.
انه من الرائع ما فعله بعض الناس.
So here's a few statistics from the project.
وهذه بعض الاحصائيات من المشروع.
Approximate collection rate of 11 sheep per hour,
تقريبا نسبة التجميع كانت 11 خروف في الساعة الواحدة،
which would make a working wage of 69 cents per hour.
مما يجعل نسبة الأجور 69 سنت "قرش" في الساعة.
There were 662 rejected sheep
كان هناك 662 خروفا رفضوا
that didn't meet "sheep-like" criteria and were thrown out of the flock.
والذين لم يتلائموا مع المعايير القياسية لشكل الخروف، وطردوا من القطيع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The amount of time spent drawing ranged from four seconds to 46 minutes.
الوقت المشتغرق في الرسم تراوح ما بين 4 ثوان و 46 ثانية.
That gives you an idea of the different types of motivations and dedication.
وهذا يعطيكم انطباع عن مختلف الدوافع والاهتمامات.
And there were 7,599 people that contributed to the project,
وكان هناك 7599 شخصا ساهموا في هذا المشروع،
or were unique IP addresses --
أو كانوا أجهزة مختلفة --
so about how many people contributed.
مما يدل على عدد المساهمين.
But only one of them out of the 7,599 said this.
ولكن واحد فقط من ال 7599 قال هذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Which I was pretty surprised by.
وهو ما اذهلني حقا.
I expected people to be wondering, "Why did I draw a sheep?"
توقعت ان يتسائل الناس، " لماذا رسمت خروفا؟"
And I think it's a pretty valid question.
وأعتقد انه تساؤل في محله.
And there's a lot of reasons why I chose sheep.
وهناك العديد من الأسباب وراء اختياري للخروف.
Sheep were the first animal
الخروف هو الحيوان الأول
to be raised from mechanically processed byproducts,
والذي انشأ من منتوجات معالجة ميكانيكيا،
the first to be selectively bred for production traits,
أول من تم التحكم في صفات ولادته،
the first animal to be cloned.
وأول حيوان يستنسخ.
Obviously, we think of sheep as followers.
من الواضح ، اننا نفكر في الخراف كتابعين.
And there's this reference to "Le Petit Prince"
وهناك المرجع ل"Le Petit Prince"
where the narrator asks the prince to draw a sheep.
حيث يطلب الراوي من الأمير رسم أن يرسم خروفا.
He draws sheep after sheep.
الأمير رسم خروفا تلو الآخر.
The narrator's only appeased when he draws a box.
الراوي اكتفى فقط لدى رسمه لصندوق.
And he says, "It's not about a scientific rendering of a sheep.
وقال:"لا يتعلق الموضوع بكيفية رسمك للخروف علميا.
It's about your own interpretation and doing something different."
وانما بتفسيرك وقيامك بشيء مختلف."
And I like that.
وقد احببت هذا.
So this is a clip from Charlie Chaplin's "Modern Times."
هذا مقطع من "الأزمنة الحديثة" لتشارلي شابلن
It's showing Charlie Chaplin dealing with some of the major changes
يظهر تشارلي شابلن وهو يتعاطى مع بعض أهم التغيرات
during the Industrial Revolution.
أثناء الثورة الصناعية.
So there were no longer shoe makers,
حيث لم يعد هناك صناع أحذية،
but now there are people slapping soles on people's shoes.
ولكن الآن هناك بعض الناس تبطن أحذية الناس.
And the whole idea of one's relationship to their work changed a lot.
و الفكرة العامة من علاقة الشخص بعمله تغيرت كثيرا.
So I thought this was an interesting clip
اعتقدت ان هذا المقطع مثير للاهتمام
to divide into 16 pieces
لتقسيمه الى 16 قطعة
and feed into the Mechanical Turk with a drawing tool.
وادخاله في "ترك الآلي" مع آلة الرسم.
This basically allowed -- what you see on the left side is the original frame,
وهذا سمح بشكل أساسي -- ما تشهد في الجانب الأيسر في الأطار الأصلي،
and on the right side you see that frame
وفي الجانب الأيمن تشاهد ذلك الإطار
as interpreted by 16 people
كما تخيله 16 شخصا
who have no idea what it is they're doing.
والذين لا يملكون أدنى فكرة عن ما يقومون به.
And this was the inspiration for a project
وهو ما كان ملهما للمشروع
that I worked on with my friend Takashi Kawashima.
والذي عملت فيه مع صديقي تاكاشي كواشيما.
We decided to use the Mechanical Turk for exactly what it was meant for,
قررنا استخدام ترك الآلي في ما صنع له خصيصا،
which is making money.
وهو صنع النقود.
So we took a hundred dollar bill and divided it into 10,000 teeny pieces,
لذا فقد جئنا بورقة من فئة 100 دولار و قسمناها الى 10,000 قطعة صغيرة،
and we fed those into the Mechanical Turk.
وأدخلنا القطع الصغيرة في ترك الآلي.
We asked people to draw what it was that they saw.
وطلبنا من الناس رسم ما رأوه.
But here there was no sheep-like criteria.
ولكن هنا، لم تكن هنالك مواصفات كما في الخروف.
People, if they drew a stick figure or a smiley face,
لو رسم الناس شخص من الأعواد أو وجه ضاحك،
it actually made it into the bill.
فقد تصبح فعلا جزء من الورقة.
So what you see is actually a representation of how well people did
وما تشاهدون الآن عرض لمدى جودة ما صنعه الناس
what it was they were asked to do.
ما طلب منهم فعله.
So we took these hundred dollar bills,
وهكذا أخذنا هذه الورقة من فئة المائة دولار،
and we put them on a website called TenThousandsCents.com,
ووضعناها على موقع يدعى TenThousandsCents.com
where you can browse through and see all the individual contributions.
حيث يمكنك التصفح ومشاهدة المساهمات الفردية.
And you can also trade real hundred-dollar bills for fake hundred-dollar bills
ويمكنكم مقايضة مائة دولار حقيقية بأخرى مزيفة
and make a donation to the Hundred Dollar Laptop Project,
والقيام بالتبرع لمشروع جهاز شخصي بمائة دولار،
which is now known as One Laptop Per Child.
والمعروفة حاليا بكمبيوتر شخصي لكل طفل.
This is again showing all the different contributions.
مرة أخرى هنا تظهر مختلف المساهمات.
You see some people did beautiful stipple renderings,
تشاهد بعض الناس قاموا بالرسم بالنقط بشكل رائع،
like this one on top --
كهذه التي في الأعلى --
spent a long time making realistic versions.
استغرق وقت طويل لصنع نسخ تبدو حقيقية.
And other people would draw stick figures or smiley faces.
وبعض الناس قد ترسم أشخاص بالعصي ووجوها ضاحكة.
Here on the right-hand side in the middle
هنا على الجانب الأيمن في الوسط
you see this one guy writing, "$0.01!!! Really?"
يمكنكم أن تشاهدوا شخصا يكتب، "$0.01 !!!! حقا؟؟"
That's all I'm getting paid for this?
هذا كل ما سيدفع لي؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So the last Mechanical Turk project I'm going to talk to you about
وهكذا المشروع الأخير التابع ل "ترك الآلي" الذي سأتحدث عنه
is called Bicycle Built for 2000.
يدعى دراجة صنعت من أجل 2000.
This is a collaboration with my friend Daniel Massey.
هذا تعاون مع صديقي دانييل ماسي.
You may recognize these two guys.
يمكنكم التعرف على هذين الشخصين.
This is Max Mathews and John Kelly from Bell Labs in the '60s,
هذا ماكس ميثيوز و جوني كيلي من معامل بيل في السيتينيات،
where they created the song "Daisy Bell,"
حيث ابتكروا أغنية "دايسي بيل،"
which was the world's first singing computer.
وهو أول حاسوب مغني في العالم.
You may recognize it from "2001: A Space Odyssey."
يمكنك التعرف عليه من فيلم "2001: A Space Odyssey."
When HAL's dying at the end of the film he starts singing this song,
عندما كا هال يحتضر في نهاية الفيلم بدأ في غناء هذه الأغنية.
as a reference to when computers became human.
كإحالة إلى حين تصير أجهزة الكمبيوتر بشرية.
So we resynthesized this song.
فأعدنا صياغة هذه الأغنية.
This is what that sounded like.
وهذا ما بدت مثله.
We broke down all the individual notes
لقد قسمنا كل نغمة على حدا
in the singing as well as the phonemes in the singing.
في الغناء وكذلك في الصوتيات في الغناء.
Daisy Bell: ♫ Daisy, Daisy ... ♫
دايزي بل: ♫ دايزي دايزي♫
Aaron Koblin: And we took all of those individual pieces,
آرون كبلن: وأخذنا كل هذه النغمات المنفردة،
and we fed them into another Turk request.
وأعدناه الى الآلي مرة أخرى.
This is what it would look like if you went to the site.
هذا ما سيبدو لو ذهبت إلى الموقع.
You type in your code,
انت تكتب في البرنامج،
but you first test your mic.
ولكن أولا تاكد من ميكروفونك.
You'd be fed a simple audio clip.
وسوف تسمع تسجيل صوتي بسيط.
(Honk)
(بوق)
And then you'd do your best to recreate that with your own voice.
ثم تبذل قصارى جهدك للحصول على نفس التسجيل الصوتي بصوتك الخاص.
After previewing it and confirming it's what you submitted,
بعد المراجعة والتأكد أنه ما أرسلته،
you could submit it into the Mechanical Turk with no other context.
يمكنك التسجيل الآلي بدون سياق.
And this is what we first got back from the very first set of submissions.
وهذا ما حصلناه في أول دفعة من البيانات.
Recording: ♫ Daisy, Daisy ♫
تسجيل: ♫ دايزي ، دايزي♫
♫ give me your answer do ♫
♫ أعطني اجابتك ♫
♫ I'm half crazy ♫
♫ لقد شارفت على الجنون ♫
♫ all for the love of you ♫
♫ كل هذا من أجل حبك ♫
♫ It can't be a stylish marriage ♫
♫ لن يكون فرحا مبهرا ♫
♫ I can't afford a carriage ♫
♫ ليس في امكاني تحمل تكاليف عربة ♫
♫ But you'll look sweet upon the seat ♫
♫ ولكن كنت ستبدين رائعة في مقعد ♫
♫ of a bicycle built for two ♫
♫ دراجة صنعت لأثنين ♫
AK: So James Surowieki has this idea of the wisdom of crowds,
آرون: جيمس سورويكي كان له فكر حكمة الحشد،
that says that a whole bunch of people are smarter than any individual.
والتي تقول ان مجموعة من الناس أذكي من أي شخص.
We wanted to see how this applies to collaborative, distributed music making,
أردنا أن نرى كيف أن هذا ينطبق على التعاون ، والتوزيع الموسيقى،
where nobody has any idea what it is they're working on.
حيث لا يدري أي من الأشخاص ما يعمل عليه.
So if you go to the BicycleBuiltforTwoThousand.com
فاذا ذهبت الى BicycleBuiltforTwoThousand.com
you can actually hear what all this sounds like together.
يمكنك سماع كل هذا فعلا ما يبدو وكأنه معا.
I'm sorry for this.
انني آسف على هذا
(Noise)
(ضجيج)
Chorus: ♫ Daisy, Daisy ♫
المجموعة:♫ دايزي ، دايزي♫
♫ Give me your answer do ♫
♫ أعطني اجابتك ♫
♫ I'm half crazy ♫
♫ لقد شارفت على الجنون ♫
♫ all for the love of you ♫
♫ كل هذا من أجل حبك ♫
♫ It can't be a stylish marriage ♫
♫ لن يكون فرحا مبهرا ♫
♫ I can't afford a carriage ♫
♫ ليس في امكاني تحمل تكاليف عربة ♫
♫ But you'd look sweet upon the seat ♫
♫ ولكن كنت ستبدين رائعة في مقعد ♫
♫ of a bicycle built for two ♫
♫ دراجة صنعت لأثنين ♫
AK: So stepping back for a quick second,
آرون : نعود القليل الى الخلف
when I was at UCLA going to grad school,
عندما التحقت بالدراسات العليا في جامعة كاليفورنيا لوس أنجلوس،
I was also working at a place called the Center for Embedded Network Sensing.
كنت أعمل في مكان يدعى مركز استشعار الشبكات.
And I was writing software to visualize laser scanners.
وكنت أكتب البرامج لرؤية الماسحات الليزرية.
So basically motion through 3D space.
بشكل أساسي الحركة في الفضائ الثلاثي الأبعاد.
And this was seen by a director in L.A. named James Frost
وهذا ما شاهده مخرج من لوس انجلوس يدعى جيمس فروست
who said, "Wait a minute.
والذي قال، "انتظر لحظة.
You mean we can shoot a music video without actually using any video?"
انت تقصد ان بامكانك تصوير فيديو موسيقى دون استخدام اي فيديو؟"
So we did exactly that.
وهذا ما فعلناه تماما.
We made a music video for one of my favorite bands, Radiohead.
صنعنا فيديو موسيقي لواحدة من الفرق المفضلة لدي ، راديوهيد.
And I think one of my favorite parts of this project
وأعتقد أن واحد من الأجزاء المفضلة لدي في هذا المشروع
was not just shooting a video with lasers,
ليس فقط تصوير الفيديو بالليزر،
but we also open sourced it,
ولكننا أيضا جعله مفتوح المصدر،
and we made it released as a Google Code project,
وأصدرناه كمشروع Google Code،
where people could download a bunch of the data and some source code
حيث يمكن للناس تحميل حفنة من البيانات وبعض الشيفرات المصدرية
to build their own versions of it.
لصنع نسختهم الخاصة منه.
And people were making some amazing things.
وكانوا يصنعون أمورا في غاية الروعة.
This is actually two of my favorites:
هذه في الواقع اثنتان من المفضلة لدي:
the pin-board Thom Yorke and a LEGO Thom Yorke.
لوحة دبابيس توم يورك وليغو توم يورك.
A whole YouTube channel of people submitting really interesting content.
قناة يوتيوب كاملة من الناس تقدم محتوى مثيرا للاهتمام حقا.
More recently, somebody even 3D-printed Thom Yorke's head,
في الآونة الأخيرة، شخص طبع رأس توم يورك ثلاثي الأبعاد،
which is a little creepy, but pretty cool.
وهو مخيف قليلا، ولكن جميل جدا.
So with everybody making so much amazing stuff
في حين أن الجميع يفعل الكثير من الاشياء المدهشة
and actually understanding what it was they were working on,
و في الواقع فهم ما كانوا يعملون عليه،
I was really interested in trying to make a collaborative project
كنت مهتم حقا بمحاولة القيام بمشروع تعاوني
where people were working together to build something.
حيث يعمل الناس معا لبناء شيء ما.
And I met a music video director named Chris Milk.
وقابلت مخرج فيديو موسيقي يدعى كريس ميلك.
And we started bouncing around ideas
وبدأنا بتجاذب الأفكار
to make a collaborative music video project.
لعمل مشروع فيديو موسيقي تعاوني.
But we knew we really needed the right person
ولكن كنا نعرف أننا بحاجة فعلا للشخص المناسب
to kind of rally behind and build something for.
إلى نوع من الاحتشاد وراءه، وبناء شيء ما.
So we put the idea on the back burner for a few months.
لذلك وضعنا الفكرة على الموقد الخلفي لبضعة أشهر.
And he ended up talking to Rick Rubin,
وانتهى بنا المطاف الى التحدث لريك روبن،
who was finishing up Johnny Cash's final album
والذي كان ينهي الألبوم الأخير لجوني كاش
called "Ain't No Grave."
يدعى "ليس هنالك قبر".
The lyrics to the leading track are "Ain't no grave can hold my body down."
كلمات الأغنية الرئيسية تقول" ليس هنالك قبر يمكنه الامساك بجسدي بالأسفل".
So we thought this was the perfect
كنا نتصور هذا هو المشروع
project to build a collaborative memorial
الكامل لبناء تذكار تشاركي
and a virtual resurrection for Johnny Cash.
وبعث افتراضي لجوني كاش.
So I teamed up with my good friend Ricardo Cabello, also known as Mr. doob,
وكونا فريق مع صديقي المخلص ريكاردو كابللو والمعروف بالسيد دوب،
who's a much better programmer than I am,
وهو مبرمج أفضل مني بكثير،
and he made this amazing Flash drawing tool.
وقد صنع اداة رسم مبهرة بالفلاش.
As you know,
وكما تعرفون،
an animation is a series of images.
الرسوم المتحركة هي عبارة عن سلسلة من الصور.
So what we did was cross-cut a bunch of archival footage of Johnny Cash,
ما فعلناه كان قطع حفنة من لقطات أرشيفية لجوني كاش،
and at eight frames a second,
وبسرعة ثمانية لقطات في الثانية،
we allowed individuals to draw a single frame
سمحنا للأفراد برسم إطار واحد
that would get woven into
والتي ستنسج داخل
this dynamically changing music video.
الفيديو الموسيقي المتغير ديناميكيا.
So I don't have time to play the entire thing for you,
ليس لدي الوقت لأريكم الفيديو كاملا،
but I want to show you two short clips.
ولكنني أريد أن أريكم مقطعين قصيرين.
One is the beginning of the music video.
أحدهما بداية الفيديو.
And that's going to be followed by a short clip
وهذا سيليه مقطع قصير
of people who have already contributed to the project
لأشخاص ساهموا في هذا المشروع
talking about it briefly.
تتحدث عنه اختصار.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Video) Johnny Cash: ♫ There ain't no grave ♫
جوني كاش :♫ ليس هناك قبر ♫
♫ can hold my body down ♫
♫ يمكنه الاحتفاظ بجسدي ♫
♫ There ain't no grave ♫
♫ ليس هناك قبر ♫
♫ When I hear the trumpet sound ♫
♫ عند سماعي صوت النفير ♫
♫ I'm going to ride right out of the ground ♫
♫ سوف انطلق خارجا من الأرض ♫
♫ Ain't no grave ♫
♫ ليس هناك قبر ♫
♫ can hold my body ... ♫
♫ يمكنه الاحتفاظ بجسدي ♫
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
AK: What better way to pay tribute to the man
آرون: ما هي أفضل طريقة لتكريم لرجل
than to make something for one of his songs.
سوى تقديم شيء لإحدى أغانيه.
Collaborator: I felt really sad when he died.
مساهم 1: شعرت بالأسى الحقيقي حين مات.
And I just thought it'd be wonderful,
وأعتقد انه سيكون من الرائع،
it'd be really nice to contribute something to his memory.
أنه سيكون جميلا حقا أن نسهم بشيء لذكراه.
Collaborator Two: It really allows
مساهم 2: إنه يسمح فعلا
this last recording of his
لهذا التسجيل الأخير له
to be a living, breathing memorial.
ان يكون ذكراه الخالدة.
Collaborator Three: For all of the frames to be drawn by fans,
مساهم 3: لجميع اللقطات التي يمكن استخلاصها من قبل المشجعين،
each individual frame,
كل لقطة على حدى،
it's got a very powerful feeling to it.
لها احساسها القوي.
Collaborator Four: I've seen everybody
مساهم 4: لقد شاهدت الجميع
from Japan, Venezuela, to the States,
من اليابان، فنزويلا، الى الولايات المتحدة،
to Knoxville, Tennessee.
الى كنوكسفيل، تينيسي.
Collaborator Five: As much as is different from frame to frame,
مساهم 5: على الرغم من الاختلاف من لقطة الى لقطة
it really is personal.
ولكنه شخصي جدا.
Collaborator Six: Watching the video in my room,
مساهم 6: عند مشاهدتي للفيديو في غرفتي
I could see me not understanding at the beginning of it.
كنت أراني غير قادر على الاستيعاب في بدايته.
And I just worked and worked through problems,
وعملت وعملت على حل المشاكل
until my little wee battles that I was fighting within the picture
حتى المعارك الاولى التي كنت اقاتلها داخل الصورة
all began to resolve themselves.
بدأت في الحل من تلقاء نفسها
You can actually see the point when I know what I'm doing,
يمكنك ان ترى حقا النقطة حيث بدأت ادراك ما أفعله
and a lot of light and dark comes into it.
والكثير من النور والظلام تداخل فيه.
And in a weird way,
وبطريقة عجيبة،
that's what I actually like about Johnny Cash's music as well.
كذلك، هذا ما أحبه فعلا في موسيقى جوني كاش.
It's the sum total of his life,
إنه نتاج حياته،
all the things that had happened --
كل الأشياء التي حدثت --
the bad things, the good things.
الأشياء السيئة والأشياء الطيبة.
You're hearing a person's life.
فأنت تستمع الى حياة شخص.
AK: So if you go to the website JohnnyCashProject.com,
آرون: أذا تصفحت موقع JohnnyCashProject.com،
what you'll see is the video playing above.
ستشاهد الفيديو يتحرك في الأعلى.
And below it are all the individual frames
وأسفله اللقطات المفردة
that people have been submitting to the project.
والتي قدمها الأفراد للمشروع.
So this isn't finished at all,
وبالتالي فانه غير منته تماما،
but it's an ongoing project where people can continue to collaborate.
ولكنه مشروع ممتد حيث يستمر الناس في التعاون.
If you roll over any one of those individual thumbnails,
اذا مررت على اي من هذه الصور المصغرة،
you can see the person who drew that individual thumbnail
بامكانك رؤية الشخص الذي رسم هذه الصورة المصغرة
and where they were located.
ومكان تواجده.
And if you find one that you're interested in,
واذا وجدت صورة منهم قد لفتت اهتمامك،
you can actually click on it and open up an information panel
فبإمكانك النقر عليها حيث تظهر لوحة معلومات
where you're able to rate that frame,
حيث بإمكانك تقييم هذه اللقطة،
which helps it bubble up to the top.
وهو ما يساعدها للوصول إلى أعلى القائمة.
And you can also see the way that it was drawn.
كما بإمكانك رؤية كيف تم رسمها.
Again, you can get the playback and personal contribution.
مرة أخرى، يمكنك أن تشاهد المساهمات.
In addition to that, it's listed, the artist's name, the location,
بالإضافة الى ذلك، فإن إسم الفنان ومكان تواجده مسجلان،
how long they spent drawing it.
وكم من الوقت استغرق في رسمها.
And you can pick a style. So this one was tagged "Abstract."
ويمكنك اختيار الاسلوب. لذلك كان هذا يدعى "الملخص".
But there's a bunch of different styles.
ولكن هناك مجموعة من أنماط مختلفة.
And you can sort the video a number of different ways.
ويمكنك فرز الفيديو بعدد من الطرق المختلفة.
You can say, "I want to see the pointillist version
يمكنك أن تقول، "أريد أن أرى إصدار بدون نقاط
or the sketchy version or the realistic version.
أو إصدار مرسوم أو إصدار واقعي.
And then this is, again, the abstract version,
وهذا مرة أخرى ، إصدار مجرد،
which ends up getting a little bit crazy.
والتي تصل في النهاية الى بعض الجنون.
So the last project I want to talk to you about is another collaboration with Chris Milk.
المشروع الأخير الذي أريد التحدث عنه هو تعاون آخر مع كريس ميلك.
And this is called "The Wilderness Downtown."
ويسمى "وسط البلد البرية ".
It's an online music video for the Arcade Fire.
هو فيديو موسيقي لفرقة The Arcade Fire.
Chris and I were really amazed
انا وكريس كنا منبهرين حقا
by the potential now with modern web browsers,
بامكانيات المتصفحات الشبكية،
where you have HTML5 audio and video
حيث لديك HTML5 صوت وصورة
and the power of JavaScript to render amazingly fast.
وقوة ال JavaScript على التصيير بسرعة مبهرة.
And we wanted to push the idea of the music video that was meant for the Web
وأردنا أن نشجع فكرة الفيديو الموسيقي المقصود من الشبكة
beyond the four-by-three or sixteen-by-nine window
غير شاشة مقاس اربعة الى ثلاثة أو 16/9
and try to make it play out and choreograph throughout the screen.
ومحاولة جعله يخرج تصميم الرقصة من الشاشة.
But most importantly, I think,
ولكن الأهم ، في اعتقادي
we really wanted to make an experience that was unlike the Johnny Cash Project,
أننا اردنا حقا صنع خبرة مختلفة عن مشروع جوني كاش،
where you had a small group of people spending a lot of time
حيث قام عدد صغير من الناس بامضاء الكثير من الوقت
to contribute something for everyone.
لتسهم بشيء لكل الناس.
What if we had a very low commitment,
ماذا لو كان لدينا التزام ضعيف،
but delivered something individually unique to each person who contributed?
ولكن قدمنا شيء منفردا لكل من ساهم؟
So the project starts off by asking you to enter the address
يبدأ المشروع بأن يطلب منك عنوان
of the home where you grew up.
المنزل الذي نشأت فيه.
And you type in the address --
وتسجل العنوان --
it actually creates a music video specifically for you,
ويقوم في الواقع بابتكار فيديو موسيقي خاص بك،
pulling in Google maps and Streetview images
مستخدما خرائط جوجل وصور للشارع
into the experience itself.
في التجربة نفسها.
So this should really be seen at home with you typing in your own address,
وهو ما يجب ان تشاهده في منزلك وانت تسجل عنوانك الخاص،
but I'm going to give you a little preview of what you can expect.
ولكني سأعطيكم فكرة عامة عما يمكنكم توقعه.
(Video) Win Butler: ♫ Now our lives are changing fast ♫
(فيديو) ون باتلر : ♫ الآن حياتنا تختلف سريعا ♫
♫ Now our lives are changing fast ♫
♫ الآن حياتنا تختلف سريعا ♫
♫ Hope that something pure can last ♫
♫ نتمنى أن يبقى شيئا نقيا ♫
♫ Ooh we used to wait ♫
♫ اعتدنا الإنتظار ♫
♫ Sometimes it never came ♫
♫ أحيانا لا تأتي أبدا ♫
♫ Still moving through the pain ♫
♫ ما زلنا نجتاز آلامنا ♫
♫ We used to wait for it ♫
♫ اعتدنا إنتظاره ♫
AK: So I think, if there's one thing to take away from my talk today,
لذا أعتقد أنه إن كانت هناك نتيجة من حديثي اليوم،
it's that an interface can be a powerful narrative device.
فهي أن الوسيط بامكانه أن يكون جهاز سرد قوي.
And as we collect more and more personally and socially relevant data,
وبينما نجمع بيانات المزيد والمزيد من البيانات الشخصية والاجتماعية،
we have an opportunity, and maybe even an obligation,
فإن لدينا الفرصة، أو ربما حتي من الواجب،
to maintain the humanity and tell some amazing stories
أن نحافظ على الإنسانية وأن نسرد بعض القصص الرائعة
as we explore and collaborate together.
في أثناء بحثنا ومساعدتنا بعضنا البعض.
Thanks a lot.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)